Okay, בוקר טוב, boker tov, today's דף daf is פ"ו, peh-vav, 86,
we're a little behind, we pick up on פ"ה עמוד ב' peh-hey
amud bet on the two dots, we are
about 15 lines down, I'd say, ואלו לא היו... v'elu lo hayu...
excuse me, אמר רבי יוחנן לא הכשיר רבי עקיבא. amar Rabbi Yochanan
lo hichshir Rabbi Akiva. Okay,
so רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva basically said that among the things that
if it עלו לא ירדו alu lo yardu would be included animals
with a בעל מום, baal mum, of course that's difficult because that's
a classic example of לא היו פסולן בקודש, lo hayu psulan bakodesh,
that they were actually already invalid before they were sanctified or even
if they got the מום mum after they were sanctified, it really
was not because of a ritual that was done incorrectly. So now
we're going to explain that position of רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. We
did this yesterday, but we'll just do this again. אמר רבי יוחנן
לא הכשיר רבי עקיבא אלא בדוקין שבעין. Amar Rabbi Yochanan lo hichshir
Rabbi Akiva ela bidukin sheba'ayin. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva only permitted when
he said that a בעל מום, baal mum, if it was up
on the מזבח, mizbeiach, you don't have to take it down, that
was only with like a sort of a small type of a
blemish, type of some type of a cataract or whatever in the
eye, הואיל וכשר בעופות, ho'il vekasher be'ofos, since it has an analogue
of something that's כשר kasher in a bird because birds, it's only
פסול pasul if it's missing a limb, so therefore that is what
allows it to stay. But otherwise, it would fall in the general
category of not having פסולו בקודש psulo bakodesh and have to be
taken down. Now, and as we mentioned yesterday, it's a little strange
because there's a lot of מומים mumim that are worse than a
cataract of the eye and that also not פסול pasul with a
bird. Bird is only completely missing a limb. So רש"י Rashi sort
of suggests that worse types of blemishes would also not be okay
because they're like מאוס, ma'os, they're like
inappropriate, excuse me,
רש"י Rashi uses the word מגונה, megunneh, not מאוס, ma'os, but some
type of a blemish that makes it seem inappropriate and not the
type of thing that you would offer to God. So it's clear
the גמרא Gemara wants to significantly limit רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva to
something that is almost invisible, but the comparison to birds would suggest
a larger category. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues: והוא שקדם
הקדישן את מומם. vehu shekadam hekdeshan es mumam.
Okay, and in trying to limit רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva even further,
we're going to say that first it was sanctified and then it
got the blemish, so that is again... that makes it closer to
the category of פסולו בקודש, psulo bakodesh, in the fact that the
פסול psul occurred after it was sanctified, although that's not exactly what
פסולו בקודש psulo bakodesh means. But again, if it got the פסול
psul before it was sanctified, then the very קדושה kedusha from the
outset is not really קדושת מזבח, kedushas mizbeiach, so it would not
therefore, if that happened, you would have to bring it down even
if עלו. alu.
Okay, ומודה רבי עקיבא, umodeh Rabbi Akiva, not only that, רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva would also agree, בעולת נקבה דכשקדם מומא להקדש דמיא, be'olas
nekeivah dekeshekadam muma lehekdesh damya,
that if somebody were to sanctify an animal that was female for
an עולה—an olah עולה olah can only be male—that that would be
like that the מום mum preceded its
sanctification, because at the moment it was sanctified it was already unfit
to be used, so it never really got a קדושה kedusha for
an עולה olah that made it fit to be offered on the
מזבח. mizbeiach. So in that case, even if עלו, alu, ירדו. yardu.
It's interesting that the גמרא Gemara sort of puts the issue of
the wrong sex into the מום mum category. This is a type
of מום mum for רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, but nevertheless, because the
מום mum preceded the הקדש, hekdesh, therefore it would have to come
down. I mean, even the גמרא Gemara recognizes it's not a מום;
mum; he says it's like the מום mum preceded. I mean, it
did precede a הקדש, hekdesh, it's just that it's not actually a
מום. mum. So maybe רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva never disagreed with the
wrong sex to begin with, but anyway, the גמרא Gemara is saying
that this would be a case that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva would
agree to because the problem came before it was sanctified. Okay, בעי
רבי ירמיה, ba'i Rabbi Yirmiyah, רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmiyah asked the following
question: יש נרבע בעופות או אין נרבע בעופות? yesh nirva be'ofos o
ein nirva be'ofos? A bird, we learn from a פסוק pasuk מן
הבהמה, min habeheimah, that you can bring a קרבן korban from the
בהמה, beheimah, but not from all בהמות, beheimos, and one of the
things that that is excluding is a בהמה beheimah that was involved
in an act of bestiality, and that's either a רובע, rove'ah, that
it penetrate... a male that penetrated a female, or a נרבע, nirva,
that it was penetrated by a male, by a male human,
so bestiality, an animal with a human. So the question is, what
would be the story with a bird that a human was... that
was penetrated by a human? Would that also be invalid? What's the
question? Let's take a look.
רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmiyah likes asking these types of questions. Okay,
או אין נרבע בעופות מי אמר מן הבהמה לא. o ein nirva
be'ofos mi amar min habeheimah lo. מן הבהמה min habihema teaches us
we exclude an animal that was either a רובע roveia or a
נרבע, nireva, and but because we exclude both, maybe they come as
a package deal. כל היכא דאיתא ברובע איתא בנרבע כל היכא דליתא
ברובע ליתא בנרבע. kol heicha de'isa beroveia isa benireva kol heicha delisa
beroveia lisa benireva. Only an animal that could be a
רובע, roveia, only of the type of an animal that could be
a רובע roveia could also be פסול pasul as a נרבע. nireva.
But a bird, there's not possible to imagine how the bird can
do an act of bestiality of penetration of a human and therefore
it can't be a רובע. roveia. So it would also not have
the invalidity of a נרבע. nireva. Do we say that?
או דילמא o dilma or do we say הרי נעבדה בה עבירה.
harei ne'evda ba aveira. We don't make this equation it has to
come as a package deal and bottom line don't even focus on
specifically רובע roveia or נרבע. nireva. Just think of it more as
an abstract category. It was used in the act of an עבירה
aveira and that itself should invalidate it. So do we have that
abstract category or is it very concrete of נרבע nireva and רובע
roveia and then maybe they come as a package deal? So אמר
רבא amar Rava said רבא Rava תא שמע ta shema come and
hear רבי עקיבא מכשיר בבעלי מומים. Rebi Akiva machshir beva'alei mumim. רבי
עקיבא Rebi Akiva permits בעלי מומים ba'alei mumim and we significantly limited
that, but the point was only בעלי מומים, ba'alei mumim, not anything
else in the משנה mishnah that was considered to be a case
of לא היה פסולו בקודש. lo haya pesulo bakodesh. And one of
the cases in the משנה mishnah that you would אם עלו ירדו
im alu yerdu would be רובע roveia and נרבע. nireva. But רבי
עקיבא Rebi Akiva doesn't agree with that. I mean, excuse me, רבי
עקיבא Rebi Akiva doesn't disagree with that. He would agree that that
would have to come down. Okay, so what does that tell us?
ואם איתא, ve'im isa, if it were true that נרבע nireva was
כשר kasher with a bird, so נכשר נמי בנרבע הואיל וכשר בעופות.
nachsher nami benireva ho'il vekasher be'ofos. So since רבי עקיבא Rebi Akiva
permits the case of a בעל מום ba'al mum with a like
a cataract in the eye because the analogue is permissible by birds
and therefore that's enough to say אם עלו לא ירדו. im alu
lo yerdu. So then if birds were כשר kasher by a case
of נרבע, nireva, he should permit an animal that's a נרבע nireva
as well because it has an analogue by birds and therefore you
should say אם עלו לא ירדו im alu lo yerdu even by
a larger animal that was a נרבע nireva because by birds that
would not be פסול. pasul. Since he doesn't say that, it must
be that he would concede that even by birds it is פסול.
pasul. So the גמרא Gemara says שמע מינה, shema mina, that is
a good proof. Now, for my money, I don't know if it's
a good proof because we've already
limited רבי עקיבא Rebi Akiva so much that it's only דוקין שבעין,
dukin sheba'ayin, it seems other blemishes even though they're כשר kasher by
birds we wouldn't allow because it's disgusting or inappropriate. It would seem
that נרבע nireva would be the same. So not exactly clear how
much it's just allowing something very very minor or really prepared to
allow anything that is כשר kasher by analogue with a bird. Okay.
אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak אף אנן
נמי תנינא af anan nami tanina we also taught this in the
משנה: mishnah: הנרבע והמוקצה והנעבד ואתנן ומחיר וטומטום ואנדרוגינוס כולם מטמאים בגדים
בבית הבליעה. hanireva vehamuktza vehane'evad ve'esnan umechir vetumtum ve'androgynos kulam metame'im begadim
beveit habeli'a. So this is a case, it's the משנה mishnah in
בכורות Bechoros that if you go ahead and you do מליקה melikah
on a bird קרבן korban but it's a פסול קרבן, pasul korban,
then the מליקה melikah isn't meaningful, right? Because normally if you would
want to שחט shacht a bird, you would have to שחט shacht
it with a knife from the front of the neck. מליקה Melikah
is with a fingernail from the back of the neck. So it's
only a כשר שחיטה kasher shechitah as it were, the bird is
מותר mutar to be eaten if it's let's say a חטאת chatas
if it is a כשר קרבן. kasher korban. But if the bird
is a פסול קרבן, pasul korban, then the מליקה melikah doesn't count
as a מליקה melikah and therefore it's a נבלה. neveilah. It's a
dead bird that you didn't שחט shacht properly. And the הלכה halachah
of a נבלה neveilah of a bird that's a נבלה neveilah is
when you swallow it, that's when it causes טומאה. tumah. Okay. So
the משנה mishnah lists the type of פסול pasul birds that a
מליקה melikah would turn it into a נבלה neveilah because it would
not be a good קרבן. korban. And what does it list? הנרבע
hanireva and the first one there, a bird that was penetrated. והמוקצה
vehamuktza something that was set aside for עבודה זרה avodah zarah והנעבד
vehane'evad worshipped ואתנן ומחיר ve'esnan umechir gift to a prostitute or exchange
for a dog וטומטום ואנדרוגינוס vetumtum ve'androgynos and טומטום tumtum and אנדרוגינוס
androgynos because even though you don't have to, it's an interesting position
in that משנה mishnah that even though a bird does not have
to, doesn't matter male or female, according to the position of the
משנה, mishnah, at least it has to be clear which one it
is. Okay. So that's that משנה mishnah over there. כולם מטמאים בגדים
בבית הבליעה. kulam metame'im begadim beveit habeli'a. So in all of those
cases the bird never could have been offered, it was a פסול
pasul bird and therefore the מליקה melikah is not good and it's
a נבלה. neveilah. So you see very clearly from that משנה, mishnah,
you really do see clearly from that משנה mishnah that a bird
that is a נרבע nireva is פסול, pasul, שמע מינה shema mina
that is a good proof. Much better proof than our case of
רבי עקיבא. Rebi Akiva. Okay. רבי חנינא סגן הכהנים, Rebi Chanina Sgan
Hakohanim, the משנה mishnah goes on to say that רבי חנינא סגן
הכהנים Rebi Chanina Sgan Hakohanim said my father in the בית המקדש
Beis Hamikdash itself would actually היה דוחה haya docha would push the
בעלי מומים ba'alei mumim off of the מזבח. mizbei'ach. Did not agree
with you רבי עקיבא, Rebi Akiva, רבי עקיבא Rebi Akiva wasn't... around
in the time of the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash and actually said
ירדו, yerdu, they have to come down. So מאי קמשמע לן? mai
kamashma lan? What's he teaching us? I mean, we already had the
תנא קמא tanna kamma that said they have to come down. איבעית
אימא מעשה קא משמע לן, Ibayseima maiseh kamashma lan, maybe he wants
to just tell us here's an actual story, I want to tell
you in practice this is how it was, and that's very weighty
because then it's you know you can debate all you want what
you think the הלכה halacha is about the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash,
I actually have evidence from what they did. ואיבעית אימא מאי דוחה
כלאחר יד, V'ibayseima mai doche k'achar yad, maybe he's trying to tell
me how they would bring it down, it would be like incidentally,
כלאחר יד. k'achar yad. Now, does that make it, you know, from
the back of the hand more respectful or less respectful? I could
think that it makes it less respectful, like, you know, you're pushing
something away with the back of your hand, like waving it off,
like you're showing your disregard for it. Okay, if you take a
look at רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi says, let's see where's רש"י, Rashi,
כלאחר יד ואין מורידן דרך בזיון בפרהסיא. k'achar yad v'ein moridan derech
bizayon b'farhesya.
So you do it in a subtle, private, incidental way so people
don't, it's not obvious to people, because to actively take something off
the מזבח, mizbeach, that would be, you know, in a visible obvious
way, that would be a denigration of it. So רש"י Rashi reads
the כלאחר יד k'achar yad as a way of doing it respectfully
and subtly. Okay, כשם שאם עלו, k'sheim she'im ala, so now the
משנה mishna goes on to say that the same way that the
things that you're allowed to keep up if they went up, you
don't bring them down, so the משנה mishna says כשם שאם
עלו לא ירדו כך אם ירדו לא יעלו. k'sheim she'im ala lo
yerdu kach im yardu lo ya'alu.
If they actually were brought down off the מזבח, mizbeach, you don't
bring them back up. And הלכה halacha is they're allowed to stay
up, but but that doesn't give them a right to go back
up if they were actually brought down yet again or they were
brought down. So the גמרא Gemara says like this: אמר עולא Amar
Ulla says עולא, Ulla, לא שנו אלא שלא משלה בהן האור. lo
shanu ela shelo mashla bahen ha'ur. That is only if the fire
has not, you know, taken seized them. Now how exact, you know,
how deep, how burnt they have to be for this category of
משלה בהן האור mashla bahen ha'ur that the fire seizes them is
not clear. תוספות Tosafot discusses it, you know, could be even something
that is relatively minimal, but the thing is actually the fire has
been burning on the thing itself. Okay, but once אבל משלה בהן
האור, aval mashla bahen ha'ur, once the fire has seized them, even
these פסול, pasul, even these, at least, excuse me, these things that
say אם עלו לא ירדו, im alu lo yerdu, then in that
case, A, you're allowed to keep it up, and B, now they've
been burning by the fire, so in that case, okay, יעלו, ya'alu,
even if they came back down, they go back up, because the
phrase sort of uses נעשה לחמו של מזבח, na'asa lachmo shel mizbeach,
like they become the bread of the מזבח, mizbeach, like לחם אשה,
lechem isheh, you know, it's, it's a לחם אשה. lechem isheh. So
once the fire is consuming them, then it already belongs on the
fire, the fire has taken possession of them and in that case,
even if they came down, they would go back up, you would
no longer look at them as something פסול, pasul, you'd look at
them as something that belongs on the מזבח. mizbeach. Now again, it
seems that we're talking only about the things אם עלו לא ירדו,
im alu lo yardu, not about things that you would have to
be מוריד. morid. But things that at least have a right to
be on the מזבח mizbeach once they were put there, at least,
you know, or right not to be taken off, once the fire
starts burning on them, then they would get put back. I have
to say that by all these discussions about things that are burning,
whether you put them back or don't put them back, there's a
question, we'll see more of this on the next דף, daf, about
whether it means you're חייב chayav to put them back or it's
מותר mutar to put them back. But minimally it means it's מותר.
mutar. Okay, so once the fire is burning, then even if it
falls off, you could put it back on.
רב מרי מתני ארישא רב חנינא מסורא מתני אסיפא. Rav Mari masni
a reisha Rav Chanina Misura masni a seifa. So this idea that
משלה בהן האור mashla bahen ha'ur makes a difference, which part of
the משנה mishna is it going, the רישא reisha of the משנה,
mishna, meaning the משנה mishna we're just wrapping up, or the סיפא,
seifa, the second part, which is actually the משנה mishna we're about
to read. Okay, so let's take a look. The משנה mishna we're
about to read, just to read the first line, ואלו אם עלו
לא ירדו, v'eilu im alu lo yerdu, well actually, I won't read
the whole line, but the end of the משנה mishna speaks about,
about the עצמות atzamot and the וגידים v'gidim and the וקרניים v'karnayim
and the וטלפיים v'tlafim of the animal, that those also are things
that, you know, that you don't, if they're, well, we'll take a
look, let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. So the גמרא
Gemara says like this:
Okay, רב חנינא מסורא מתני אסיפא, Rav Chanina Misura masni a seifa,
עצמות וגידים וקרניים וטלפיים, atzamot v'gidim v'karnayim v'tlafim,
so this is a סיפא, seifa, it's the end of the משנה
mishna we're about to read. The bones and the sinews and the
horns and the hoofs בזמן שמחוברים יעלו, bizman shemechubarim ya'alu,
if they are still attached to the animal and this would be,
let's say, an עולה olah where you burn the limbs, then you
bring them up, you know, you bring up the leg with the,
with the hoof, you bring up the head with
the horn. Okay, בזמן שמחוברים יעלו פירשו לא יעלו. bizman shemechubarim ya'alu
pirshu lo ya'alu. If they were separated, you know, from down on
the floor of the בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash* from the head, the
horns came off or the hooves were taken off, then you don't
put them on the מזבח Mizbeach, *Mizbeach*. Okay, so here's a הלכה
*halacha* that you don't put them on,
and comes along and אמר עולא *Amar Ulla*, so now does this
statement of עולא *Ulla* apply even to this? Okay, even to these
things like the horns, or is he just applying to the things
that we said that certain invalidities which were אם עלו לא ירדו
alu lo yerdu. *im alu lo yerdu*? So here we're applying it
even to the סיפא *seifa*. אמר עולא *Amar Ulla*: לא שנו אלא
שלא משלה בהן האור *Lo shanu ela shelo mashla bahen ha'ohr*. This
idea that these things don't get put back on the מזבח mizbeach,
*Mizbeach*, the horns and the hooves and whatever, is only if the
fire hasn't taken hold of them. אבל משלה בהן האור יעלו ya'alu,
*Aval mashla bahen ha'ohr ya'alu*, but if the fire took hold of
them and then they flew off the מזבח mizbeach, *Mizbeach*, then you
would bring them back up, okay. Now you can imagine this in
like one of two scenarios. One is this is all going to
get very complicated and we're going to get to this, but one
is you brought up the leg with the hoof, which you were
supposed to do, okay, and then it was burning on the fire,
and because it was burning on the fire, the hoof separated and
then it flew off. And then what עולא *Ulla* is saying is,
even though when it was separated at the bottom before you brought
it up, if it was off you don't bring it up, but
if you brought it up legitimately and the fire burned it and
then it flew off, then you would be allowed to bring it
back up. Okay, that's one way of understanding עולא *Ulla*. Another way
is actually it was separated at the bottom, you weren't supposed to
bring it up, you did bring it up, maybe that would also
have the הלכה *halacha* אם עלו לא ירדו yerdu *im alu lo
yerdu*, okay, and then but if it had fallen off you wouldn't
restore it. If it was ירדו yerdu. *yerdu* you wouldn't put it
back, but משלה בהן האור *mashla bahen ha'ohr*, if it falls off
you do put it back. All right, and it's all very hard
to keep track of all this. But bottom line is עולא *Ulla*
is saying the things that if they were at the bottom you
don't bring them up, משלה בהן האור *mashla bahen ha'ohr*, when they
were put on the מזבח mizbeach, *Mizbeach* and משלה בהן האור *mashla
bahen ha'ohr*, that would allow you to put it back up. And
there's a question: Is he applying it just to the type of
פסולים *psulim* of אם עלו לא ירדו yerdu. *im alu lo yerdu*,
or is he applying it even to the bones and the hooves
and so on? So the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* says like
this: מאן דמתני אסיפא כל שכן ארישא *Man demasni aseifa kol shekein
areisha*. If you
say that עולא *Ulla*'s principle of
משלה בהן האור *mashla bahen ha'ohr* applies to the סיפא *seifa*, to
the case of
hooves and horns and so on, that if they fly off you
put it back up, it certainly applies to the רישא *reisha* to
the case of פסולים *psulim* that if they fly off you put
it back up once משלה בהן האור *mashla bahen ha'ohr*. However, ומאן
דמתני ארישא *u'man demasni areisha*, but if you said that it applied
to the case of the פסולים *psulim*, אבל אסיפא לא בני הקטרה
haktara נינהו *aval aseifa lo bnei haktara ninhu*, that does not mean
that you would apply it to the case of the hooves and
the horns. Those things are never something that would ever by themselves
deserve to go on the מזבח mizbeach, *Mizbeach*. Okay? So if you
compare the two cases, you have an actual limb of an עולה
olah *ola*, but the עולה olah *ola* was פסול pasul *posul* for
some reason, חוץ לזמנו *chutz l'zmano* or חוץ למקומו *chutz l'mkomo* or
whatever, and you have another thing which is you have a hoof.
All right, so I might think the thing that's more problematic is
the thing that has a פסול pasul, *psul*, but the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* is actually saying no, at some level the hoof by itself
is more problematic because you never would bring a hoof by itself
on the מזבח mizbeach, *Mizbeach*, but you would classically bring the leg
of an עולה olah *ola* on a מזבח mizbeach, *Mizbeach*. So if
you compare those two, they both you don't put them on the
מזבח mizbeach *Mizbeach*, but if you put them you keep them there.
If they fall down you don't put them back. But what if
you put them up and the fire took hold of them and
then they fell down? Do you put them back? So the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says if you say that's true about the hooves, you
would certainly say it's true about the leg of the פסול עולה
olah *posul ola*, okay, because but if you say it's true about
the leg of the פסול עולה olah *posul ola*, you would not
necessarily say you ever put the hoof back up because the hoof
is fundamentally something that you would never put on the מזבח mizbeach.
*Mizbeach* by itself. All right, and so now let's take a look
at the next משנה mishna *mishna*. ואלו *V'eilu*, now we're getting to
the משנה mishna. *mishna* where essentially we've already preempted it. ואלו אם
עלו ירדו *V'eilu im alu yerdu*: The following things, if you put
them up you have to bring them down. We already listed things
that are פסול בקודש *posul bakodesh*, let's take a look at other
things. בשר basar, קדשי קדשים kodshim *Basar kadshei kodashim*, things that don't
belong on the מזבח mizbeach *Mizbeach* to begin with, okay, meat of
קדשי קדשים kodshim? *kadshei kodashim* that aren't an עולה olah *ola*, like
a חטאת *chatas*; בשר basar, קדשים kodshim קלים *basar kadashim kalim* or
meat of קדשים kodshim, קלים *kadashim kalim* like a שלמים *shlamim*; מותר
mutar, העומר *mosar ha'omer*, the remainder of the עומר *Omer* which was
eaten by the כהנים Kohanim *kohanim*; ושתי הלחם *u'shtei halechem*, the שתי
הלחם *shtei halechem* also eaten by the כהנים *kohanim* on שבועות *Shavuos*.
ולחם הפנים, לחם הפנים lechem hapanim eaten by the כהנים also, all
these things are eaten, they don't belong on the מזבח, so if
they were put up, you take them down, okay,
ושירי מנחות, v'shiyarei menachos, all the remainder of a מנחה mincha also
would be eaten, והקטורת v'haktoret and the קטורת ktoret that was burned
on the inner מזבח, it does not belong on the outer מזבח,
so even though it is something that is burned, it never belongs
on the outer
מזבח, שאם עלו ירדו. she'im alu yerdu. Now, new point, okay, and
this is circling back to what we had just discussed. הצמר שבראשי
כבשים, hatzemer sheberashei kevasim, the wool that's on the heads of the
sheep, ושער שבזקן תישים, v'sa'ar shebizkan tishim, okay, and the hair
from the beards of goats, והעצמות והגידים והקרנים והטלפים, v'ha'atzamot v'hagidim v'hakarnayim
v'hatalafim, and the bones and the sinews and the horns and the
hooves, בזמן שהם מחוברים יעלו, bizman shehem mechubarim ya'alu, if they're still
attached, and this is about an עולה olah to this part of
the animal, you put them on the מזבח, שנאמר והקטיר הכהן את
הכל, shene'emar v'hiktir hakohen et hakol, you put it all up, including
the hooves and the horns as long as they're part of the
meat and the blood that you are offering up. But however, פירשו,
pirshu, once they were separated, then at the floor of the מזבח,
not at the top, לא יעלו, lo ya'alu, you don't bring them
up by themselves, שנאמר ועשית עולותיך הבשר והדם, shene'emar v'asita olotecha habasar
v'hadam, the Torah emphasizes that the עולה olah is the meat and
the blood, not the other stuff. So the way you reconcile this
is if it's all one, you put it up, once it's separated
you don't put it up. And this is the type of thing
we said that's not just פסול but fundamentally belongs but is פסול,
it's something that by itself doesn't belong at all, and hence the
question about what happened about משלה האור mashla ha'or and fell off
etc. But our משנה mishna. says certainly as a starting point you
never bring them up by itself. Okay, let's take a look at
the גמרא. Gemara תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, והקטיר הכהן את הכל המזבחה,
v'hiktir hakohen et hakol hamizbecha, offer it all up, לרבות העצמות והגידים
והקרנים והטלפים, lerabot ha'atzamot v'hagidim v'hakarnayim v'hatalafim, okay, again the horns and
the hooves etc. יכול אפילו פירשו, yachol afilu pirshu, maybe even if
they separated you would offer them up, תלמוד לומר ועשית עולותיך הבשר
והדם, talmud lomar v'asita olotecha habasar v'hadam, just like our משנה. mishna
אי בשר ודם, i basar vadam, if you just offer up meat
and flesh, top of פ"ה עמוד א, pei hei amud aleph, יכול
יחלוץ גידים ועצמות ויעלה בשר לגבי מזבח, yachol yachalotz gidim v'atzamot v'ya'aleh
basar legabei mizbeach, maybe you have an obligation to remove the horns
and the hooves to really fulfill the פסוק pasuk of the meat
and the flesh, you should actively remove the horns and the hoof
and never bring that up on the מזבח, תלמוד לומר talmud lomar
no, והקטיר הכהן את הכל, v'hiktir hakohen et hakol, you know, you
do offer it all up. הא כיצד, ha ketzad, how is this
the case? מחוברים יעלו, mechubarim ya'alu, if they're attached it's totally fine
to bring it up. It sounds like it's never exactly clear which
is the preference. Is it would it be better to separate? But
it sounds like no, the normal way to do it is you
bring it all up, את הכל. et hakol. So as long as
they're still attached and they haven't separated, that's what you should do,
bring it all up. פירשו, pirshu, if they separated, אפילו הם בראש
המזבח ירדו, afilu hem berosh hamizbeach yerdu, even if they're at the
top of the מזבח they get taken down. Now this was not
clear in our משנה. mishna Our משנה mishna, said לא יעלו, lo
ya'alu, you don't put them on the מזבח. It never said ירדו
that you have to take them down. So the ברייתא braita here
actually goes one step further. So let's take a look what the
גמרא Gemara's says. מאן תנא דשמיע ליה דאמר פירשו ירדו, man tanna
deshameia leh de'amar pirshu yerdu, which is the תנא tanna that holds
that if they separate not only should it be לא יעלו lo
ya'alu which is what our משנה Mishnah says, but if even if
you did put it up you have to actively bring them down.
Okay, רבי היא, Rebbi hi, that's רבי. Rebbi. דתניא detanya we taught
a ברייתא, braita, והקטיר הכהן את הכל המזבחה, v'hiktir hakohen et hakol
hamizbecha, you offer it all up, לרבות העצמות והגידים והקרנים והטלפים. lerabot
ha'atzamot v'hagidim v'hakarnayim v'hatalafim. Okay, all the bones and the whatever the
horns and the hoof. אפילו פירשו, afilu pirshu, okay,
אפילו פירשו, afilu pirshu, even now, this is going beyond what we
said in our משנה, Mishnah, even if they separated you offer them
up. אלא מה אני מקיים ועשית עולותיך הבשר והדם, ela mah ani
mekayem v'asita olotecha habasar v'hadam, so what about the fact that it
says no it's only supposed to be the meat and the flesh?
לומר לך, lomar lach, to tell you, איכולי עולה אתה מחזיר ואי
אתה מחזיר איכולי גידים ועצמות, ichulei olah atah machazir v'ei atah machazir
ichulei gidim v'atzamot, that this is sort of echoes a little bit
the stuff before about משלה האור, mashla ha'or, not exactly the same
scenario. Things that have been consumed by the fire, if it's actually
the בשר, the בשר ודם basar vadam but the בשר, then you
have a responsibility if it flies off the fire you have a
responsibility to put it back. Whereas if it's these things, the bones
and the sinews, okay, because it's not בשר ודם, basar vadam, you
don't have a responsibility to put it back. Okay, this is somewhat
parallel again to משלה האור mashla ha'or תוספות Tosafot tries to figure
it all out. But this is the תנא קמא. Tanna Kamma. So
the simple sense of this תנא קמא Tanna Kamma is actually even
if it's separated below you have a חיוב chiyuv to put it
up, and the only difference is if it flies off then you
don't put it back, okay, you don't have to put it back.
רבי אומר, Rebbi omer, now רבי Rebbi says no.
כתוב אחד אומר והקטיר הכהן את הכל המזבחה, katuv echad omer v'hiktir
hakohen et hakol hamizbecha, ריבה, riba, everything. וכתוב אחד אומר ועשית עולותיך
הבשר. vekatuv echad omer v'asita olotecha habasar. No, only the flesh and
the meat. הכיצד, Ha keitzad, how do you reconcile it? מחוברים יעלו,
mechubarim ya'alu, if they are still as one unit you put it
up, פירשו, pirshu, and but if they separate, אפילו הן בראש המזבח
ירדו, afilu hein berosh hamizbeiach yerdu, even at the top of the
המזבח mizbeiach you bring it down. So this way of reading it,
there could actually be up to three positions. The position of רבי
Rebbe that even if it was even if it was יעלו ירדו,
ya'alu yerdu, the משנה Mishnah. which only says לא יעלו, lo ya'alu,
but it might be that according to our משנה, Mishnah if it
was יעלו, ya'alu, you would you would not bring it down. And
the תנא קמא, Tanna Kamma, that and the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma
of this ברייתא Braitah that sounds like even if they were separated
below, you bring it up separately. But both רש״י Rashi and תוספות
Tosafot could have conflate them into two positions, except different ways. רש״י
Rashi says רבי Rebbe is the תנא Tanna of our משנה. Our
משנה when it says לא יעלו lo ya'alu is also would say
that if it was יעלו, ya'alu, it would be ירדו. That's רבי,
Rebbe, okay, and then you have a more radical position that even
if it's separated below you would bring it up. תוספות Tosafot goes
the other way. No, no, no. Our
the רבי Rebbe is the most extreme position, the position that ירדו.
The position of the ברייתא Braitah that says if they separate יעלו,
he says that doesn't mean if they separate at the floor of
the of the at in the מקדש Mikdash you bring it up
separately. Nobody says you bring it up separately, says תוספות. Tosafot. What
it means is, if they were separated at the top of the
המזבח, mizbeiach, you can put them on the fire, meaning if there
was עלו לא ירדו. All right, so you have three possibilities, but
רש״י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot in different ways conflate it to two.
Number one, the possibility of even if it's separated below, bring it
up. Number two, don't bring it up, but if you bring it
up, don't bring it down. And number three, רבי, Rebbe, if you
bring even if you bring it up, bring it down. Okay.
So now the גמרא Gemara says like this, פירשו לא יעלו. pirshu
lo ya'alu. Okay, once they were separated, you should not anyway, there's
a whole question here of the גרסא, girsa, the better גרסא girsa
is on the side פירשו ירדו. pirshu yerdu. Once it was separated,
you have to bring it down. It's commenting on רבי's Rebbe's position.
Okay. So אמר רבי זירא, Amar Rabbi Zeira, לא שנו אלא שפירשו
כלפי מטה. lo shanu ela shepirshu klapei mata. אבל
פירשו כלפי מעלה, aval pirshu klapei ma'ala, קרובי הוא דאקריביה לאוכלא. kruvei
hu d'akrivei l'ochla. So you went ahead and you put this leg
with the hoof up on the המזבח. mizbeiach. And as it's burning,
the hoof falls off. Well, that's a case of פירשו. pirshu. So
according to רבי Rebbe you have to go grab the hoof and
bring it down? So that's what רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira is saying.
No, if when the hoof separates off, it's moving away from the
fire, then okay, now it's not on the fire, it's moving away,
now you have to bring it down. Okay, but if it was
moving towards the fire, then it is still considered as one and
it's part of the burning of it, and that's not considered a
case of פירשו. pirshu. That's considered a case of in the process
of being burned, and you would not have to bring it down
according to רבי. Rebbe. So the גמרא Gemara... now the next two
words רש״י Rashi says like it just seems like the גמרא's Gemara
missing something. It's sort of just but the way רש״י Rashi reads
it is, באמת ואפילו פירשו, ba'emes v'afilu pirshu, like is that really
true according to רבי Rebbe that even if it separated and went
towards the fire, that you would be allowed to leave it? Now
again, it's not burning on the fire, but it's up on the
head of the המזבח, mizbeiach, and the hoof came off but it
went towards the fire. So it's a reasonable position to say that
doesn't count as פירשו, pirshu, but the גמרא Gemara is saying no,
that doesn't make sense, that would be a פירשו pirshu even according
to רבי. Rebbe. So אמר רבא הכי קאמר. Amar Rava hachi ka'amar.
So רבא Rava says fine, fine, forget this question about going towards
the fire or away from the fire. Here's what we're really trying
to say. לא שנו אלא שפירשו לאחר זריקה. lo shanu ela shepirshu
l'achar zerika. When does רבי Rebbe say that you have to bring
it down? If it separated from the leg or whatever after you
did the זריקת הדם. zerikas hadam. So whether it separated at the
bottom, whether it separated at the top of the המזבח, mizbeiach, you
did the זריקת הדם zerikas hadam and then it separated. That's when
you would have to bring it down. Okay, אבל
פירשו קודם זריקה,
aval pirshu
kodem zerika, עשה זריקה ושריתינהו, asa zerika v'shariseinhu, אפילו למעבד מינייהו קתתי
דסכינא. afilu l'mevad mineihu katatei d'sakina. Okay, but because when in that
scenario, when they were combined when you did the זריקה, zerika, they
were all defined as fit for the המזבח mizbeiach at some level
because they it was combined and therefore you would have brought it
all up, the the hoof together with the leg. Then when it's
separated, this thing that should have belonged on the המזבח mizbeiach but
now is not entitled to be brought up by itself, that has
to be brought down and that has to be disposed of properly,
it's קדשים פסולים kodshim psulim is basically the way we would look
at it. But if they were separated before you did the זריקת
הדם, zerikas hadam, then according to this idea, the זריקת הדם zerikas
hadam only relates to the part of the קרבן korban that you're
supposed to be putting up. So since it's not part of the
leg now, the זריקת הדם zerikas hadam only relates to the leg.
The leg is now designated as the thing that goes on the
המזבח. mizbeiach. The hoof has nothing to do with the קרבן. korban.
It's not a piece of the קרבן korban that you're מקריב makriv
when it's together, but then if it's separated then you have to
deal, then it's a problem you have to deal with. No, it
was never part of the קרבן. korban. The זריקה zrika applied only
to the leg. The hoof was separated already, and therefore in that
case you can use the hoof and the bones to do anything
you want. The כהן kohen can even make it like a handle
for a knife. Okay, it's not קדשים at all. All right, so
that is a fascinating distinction. How much are the bones and whatever
part of the קדשים? So according to this, it depends if they
were one with the meat during the זריקה, zrika, then they are,
and then the question is put it all up as one, if
it got separated don't put it up, dispose of it properly. But
if they were separated before the זריקה, zrika, then they're not part
of the קדשים at all. Okay, that's a fascinating position.
So סבר לה כהא, savar lah keha, so this reading of רבא
Rava holds כי הא דאמר רבי יוחנן משום רבי ישמעאל, ki ha
de'amar Rabbi Yochanan mishum Rabbi Yishmael,
like רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says in the name of רבי ישמעאל.
Rabbi Yishmael. נאמר, ne'emar, it says לא יהיה בעולה, lo yihiyeh ba'olah,
it says that the skin, the leather of the עולה olah לא
יהיה lo yihiyeh goes to the כהן. kohen. ונאמר לא יהיה באשם,
vene'emar lo yihiyeh ba'asham, and it says by the אשם asham that
the meat of the אשם asham goes to the כהן. kohen. מה
אשם עצמותיו מותרים, mah asham atzmosav mutarin,
the same way by an אשם asham the bones of an אשם
asham are permissible. Now it's not clear how we know that, maybe
the פסוק pasuk only meant the meat. But you know רשי Rashi
doesn't deal with that, but to some degree since the אשם asham
is not supposed to be burnt on the מזבח other than the
אימורים, imurim, so if it says לא יהיה lo yihiyeh it means
he can use the whole thing, okay, the meat and the bones.
So אף עולה עצמות מותרין. af olah atzmos mutarin. So even by
an עולה olah, the bones are permissible. Okay, and the bones are,
you're not going to consume them. Meat has to be consumed in
a day, the bones last. So if the תורה Torah is telling
you the bones are permissible, it means permissible to make use for
whatever you want, even for like a handle of a knife. Okay,
so since it says by an אשם asham it's his, לא יהיה,
lo yihiyeh, and that would include the bones, and from there we
would learn that the bones you could use for any personal use
that you want, and you can't obviously apply the same rules as
the meat to the bones. So therefore by an עולה olah, even
though an עולה olah is fully burnt, לא יהיה lo yihiyeh even
though it's talking about the leather, also applies to things like the
leather, the bones, and the horns and so on. Okay, now the
גמרא... Gemara and again we're saying that's if they separated before the
זריקה. zrika. So now the גמרא says מופני, mufni, actually those לא
יהיהs, lo yihiyeh those words are extra. מופני mufni means they're not
needed to do anything else, so they're totally free like to make
a strong bond for a גזירה שוה gezeirah shavah so that even
if you, so that they are impervious to logical challenges, okay, because
they're there just to make that bond. Okay,
דאי לא מופני, de'ee lo mufni, if those words weren't extra, איכא
למפרך, ika lemifrach, you can ask: One minute. מה לאשם שכן בשרו
מותר. mah le'asham shekein besaro mutar. So by a, by an אשם
asham of course the bones are מותר, mutar. the meat is מותר.
mutar. You can't just say oh therefore by analogy by an עולה
olah the bones should be מותר. But if you have a real
strong גזירה שוה gezeirah shavah that's impervious to challenge, that's what it
would tell you. So the גמרא says no, לא יהיה יתירה כתיבי.
lo yihiyeh yeteirah ketivi. It doesn't have to be that these words
are totally open and extra and not used for anything else. The
reality is that it says לא יהיה, lo yihiyeh, you know, it
didn't have to say לא יהיה lo yihiyeh at all, so the
לא יהיה lo yihiyeh is extra to begin with. It's a little
slight difference between the idea of מופני mufni and extra, okay. מופני
mufni means that it's like not being used for another purpose. לא
יהיה lo yihiyeh was sort of that it was completely superfluous to
begin with, but it's basically the same point. We have these words
and that lets us tell us that even though the logic isn't
the same, by an עולה olah you get to keep the bones.
Alright, and now we're saying if they were separated before the זריקת
דם.
zrikat
dam. מתיב רב אדא בר אהבה. metiv Rav Adda bar Ahava. רב
אדא בר אהבה Rav Adda bar Ahava challenges that, this idea that
the bones of an עולה are permissible,
separated or not separated. Here we have a תוספתא Tosefta that says
the following: עצמות קדשים לפני זריקה מועלין בהן. atzmos kodshim lifnei zrika
moalin bahen. The bones of קדשים, meaning anything other than an עולה,
before the זריקת דם zrikat dam there's מעילה me'ilah because the זריקת
דם zrikat dam is what makes the meat permissible, so it makes
everything permissible including the bones. Okay, לאחר זריקה אין מועלין בהן, le'achar
zrika ein moalin bahen,
once there's been a זריקה zrika and it permits the meat, so
there's also no problem with the bones. That's sort of what we
were saying about the
אשם. asham. ושל עולה, veshel olah, but the תוספתא Tosefta goes on
and says, but by an עולה, מועלין בהן לעולם, moalin bahen le'olam,
there's always מעילה me'ilah before and after זריקה zrika because every, you
know, עולה is supposed to be all burnt, so it seems like
it doesn't matter whether they were separated before after זריקה, zrika, bones
of an עולה are always off limits. So that's a pretty big
challenge. So the גמרא says no, אימא ושל עולה, eima veshel olah,
no, we'll read in our distinction. ושל עולה, veshel olah, by an
עולה it matters whether they, when they were separated. פירשו לפני זריקה,
pirshu lifnei zrika, if they were separated before זריקה, zrika, אין מועלין
בהן, ein moalin bahen, then totally. yours to use. The זריקה *zrika*
never applied to them, they were never part of the קרבן *korban*.
לאחר זריקה *Le'achar zrika*, if they separated after זריקה *zrika*, in that
case מועלין בהם *mo'alin bahem*, they are קודש *kodesh* and, you know,
when when they were connected with זריקה *zrika*, they were obligated to
be put on the מזבח *mizbe'ach* together with the leg. Now that
they got separated, it's like קדשים פסולים *kodshim psulim* and you have
to dispose of it. Okay. ופליגי דרבי אלעזר *U'pligi d'Rabbi Eleazar* and
this argues on רבי אלעזר *Rabbi Eleazar*, דאמר רבי אלעזר *d'amar Rabbi
Eleazar* פירשו לפני זריקה *pirshu lifnei zrika*, he says the reverse. If
they separated before זריקה *zrika*, מועלין בהם *mo'alin bahem*, that's when there's
מעילה *me'ila*, okay, why? Because רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says that in that
case they were never fit for being offered up, they were separated
but they were קודש *kodesh*, so they are part of the קרבן
*korban* but never fit for being offered up, so it's something קודש
*kodesh* that never had a שעת היתר *sh'at heter*, that never became
permissible, the זריקה *zrika* never applied to it, but it was part
of the קרבן *korban*. So the exact opposite of what we were
saying before, not stops being part of the קרבן *korban*, it's part
of the קרבן *korban* without the זריקה *zrika* applying to it and
therefore there's always מעילה *me'ila*. לאחר זריקה *Le'achar zrika* לא נהנין ולא
מועלין *lo nehenin v'lo mo'alin*, but if they were separated after זריקה
*zrika*, the זריקת הדם *zrikat hadam* made it permissible, okay, and this,
you know, or made it at least permissible to the מזבח *mizbe'ach*,
and once that's true there's no מעילה *me'ila*, and even if they
get into a state where they separate and you don't put it
on the מזבח *mizbe'ach*, the זריקת הדם *zrikat hadam* at least took
it out of the category of מעילה *me'ila*. So there's no מעילה
*me'ila*, but מדרבנן *miderabbanan* you're not supposed to benefit from it. Okay.
Okay, moving on to the next משנה *mishna*. It's hard to keep
all of this in our head. Okay. וכולן שפקעו מעל גבי המזבח
לא יחזיר *V'kulan she'paku me'al gabi hamizbe'ach lo yachzir*. All of these
things that again that of the פסול קרבנות korbanos, *pasul korbonot* or
of the bones or whatever, you know, where we say עלו לא
ירדו *alu lo yerdu*, if they flew off of the מזבח *mizbe'ach*
you don't put them back up. That's we've been saying that already.
It's sort of like ירדו לא יעלו *yerdu lo ya'alu*, if you
brought them down you don't bring them back up, also if they
flew off the מזבח *mizbe'ach* and they were on the fire and
they flew off you don't bring them back up, although we had
a discussion before about משלה בהן האור *mishla bahen ha'ur*. וכן גחלת
שפקעה מעל גבי המזבח לא יחזיר *V'chen gachelet she'paka me'al gabi hamizbe'ach
lo yachzir*. Similarly if you have a piece of charcoal that flies
off of the מזבח *mizbe'ach*, nothing פסול *pasul* at all, don't put
it back up. So really don't, you're not allowed? So רש"י Rashi
*Rashi* says the לא יחזיר *lo yachzir* of the משנה *mishna* is
you're not required to put it back up, okay, so there's that
whole question about required, allowed, forbidden. So רש"י Rashi, *Rashi* reads the
משנה *mishna* that you're not required to put it back up by
the גחלת *gachelet* and maybe even by these פסולים *psulim* or whatever,
but the פסולים *psulim* makes more sense to say you're not permitted
to put it back up, but by the גחלת *gachelet* you're not
required. לא יחזיר *Lo yachzir*. אברים שפקעו מעל גבי המזבח *Eivarim she'paku
me'al gabi hamizbe'ach*. Now let's hear, let's move on from all these
פסול *pasul* things that shouldn't be on them and a little bit
get burnt and then fly off, etc., etc. Let's just talk about
straight קרבן *korban*. You have the limbs of an עולה *Olah* that
is burning on the מזבח *mizbe'ach* and they flew off the מזבח
*mizbe'ach* when they were burning. קודם חצות chatzos. יחזיר *Kodem chatzot yachzir*.
Before חצות chatzos *chatzot* and this clearly it's a כשר קרבן *kasher
korban*, so here clearly יחזיר *yachzir* means you have to put it
back up. ומועלין בהן *U'mo'alin bahen* and there's still מעילה *me'ila*, okay,
because, you know, it's not yet done with the מצוה *mitzvah*. It's
true that the זריקה *zrika* as we said before, you know, is
part of the process of making it fit for the מזבח *mizbe'ach*,
but by this case of an עולה *Olah*, it is not yet
done with the מצוה *mitzvah* while the limbs still have to burn,
so there still is מעילה *me'ila*. לאחר חצות chatzos, *Le'achar
chatzot*, however, after midnight, לא יחזיר *lo yachzir*, then somehow magically it's
considered like they were already burned by midnight, don't, you don't have
to put it back up, ואין מועלין בהן *v'ein mo'alin bahem*, there's
no מעילה *me'ila*. It's quite bizarre, why does midnight matter? We'll see
about that in the גמרא *Gemara*. But this is where we're going
to focus. We're done with these case about the פסולים *psulim* and
the horns and whatnot. We're just going to focus in on normal
stuff that is burning, when do I have to put it back
on the מזבח *mizbe'ach*, you know, when do I not? When is
it consider and similarly when is there מעילה *me'ila* or when is
not? When is there still a מצוה *mitzvah* to burn it and
when is it done with that מצוה *mitzvah* of burning it?
Okay. כשם שהמזבח מקדש את הראוי לו כך הכבש מקדש *Keshem she'hamizbe'ach
mekadesh et haraui lo kach hakevesh mekadesh*. The same way the מזבח
*mizbe'ach* sanctifies, the ramp sanctifies. כשם שהמזבח והכבש מקדשין *Keshem she'hamizbe'ach v'hakevesh
mekadeshin* and the same way the מזבח *mizbe'ach* and the ramp sanctify
and things say לא ירדו *lo yerdu*, you know, that you don't
bring them down, etc., you know, את הראוי להם *et haraui lahem*,
כך הכלים מקדשים *kach hakelim mekadeshim*. The same is true about the
כלי קודש *klei kodesh*, about the כלי שרת *klei sharet*. Okay, so
a lot of things to see, but we are basically done for
the moment with all these פסולים *psulim*, עלו לא ירדו *alu lo
yerdu*, and we're going to really focus in on this idea about
when the קרבן *korban* is burning, when is it done, when is
there no more מעילה *me'ila*, when do you not have to put
it back up on the מזבח *mizbe'ach*. Let's take a look. at
the גמרא *Gemara*. Okay, the גמרא *Gemara*, היכי דמי *heichi dami*, what's
the case? That חצות chatzos, *chatzos* matters? גמרא *Gemara* asks a very
straightforward question. אי דאית בהו ממש *i de-is behu mamash*, if the
thing still has some meat there, it's not totally burned, so אפילו
אחר חצות chatzos, נמי *afilu achar chatzos nami* even after חצות *chatzos*,
the מצוה *mitzvah* isn't done, there should still be מעילה *me'ila* and
you should still have to put it back up on the מזבח
*mizbeach*. אי דלית בהו ממש *i de-las behu mamash*, and if the
thing has been totally burned, אפילו קודם חצות נמי לא *afilu kodem
chatzos nami lo*, even before חצות *chatzos*, the מצוה *mitzvah*'s done. How
does חצות *chatzos* make a difference? Very reasonable question. לא צריכא *lo
tzricha*, no, you need it says the גמרא *Gemara*, top of פ"ו
עמוד ב' *pei vav amud beis*, בשרירי *b'shariri*, stuff that is like
hardened meat, like the fire has burned it to the point that,
you know, it's like all of the moisture has been burned away,
but it is not yet charcoal and ash. Okay, so it is
in this, you know, middle position. Is it considered consumed or not?
And for those, that thing, we will say חצות *chatzos* matters. Where
do we learn that from? מנני מילי *minani mili*, where do we
learn this from? אמר רב *amar Rav*, says רב *Rav*, כתוב אחד
אומר *kasuv echad omer*, one פסוק *pasuk* says, כל הלילה *kol halayla*.
You know, it says by the תרומת הדשן terumat hadeshen. *trumas hadeshen*,
it says, you know, זאת תורת העלה היא העלה על מוקדה על
המזבח כל הלילה עד הבקר ואש המזבח תוקד בו *zos toras haola
hi haola al mokda al hamizbeach kol halayla ad haboker v'eish hamizbeach
tukad bo*. So, it, you know, the stuff burns on the מזבח
*mizbeach* the whole night, the עולה *ola*, and then it says והרים
את הדשן *v'herim es hadeshen* and then says the כהן *kohein* now
does the תרומת הדשן terumat hadeshen, *trumas hadeshen*, you know, and he
takes off the ashes. Okay, so it says כל הלילה והקטיר *kol
halayla v'hiktir*. So the beginning of the פסוק *pasuk* is the stuff
burns on the מזבח *mizbeach* the whole night. That's how the פסוק
*pasuk* starts, about an עולה *ola*, beginning of צו *Tzav*. כתוב אחד
אומר *kasuv echad omer*, and another פסוק *pasuk* says, כל הלילה והרים
*kol halayla v'herim*. Now it's not really another פסוק *pasuk*, it's after
it says that the whole thing burns, you know, זאת תורת העלה
היא העלה על מוקדה על המזבח כל הלילה עד הבקר ואש המזבח
תוקד בו *zos toras haola hi haola al mokda al hamizbeach kol
halayla ad haboker v'eish hamizbeach tukad bo*. Okay, after all of that
then it says, you know, speaks about the תרומת הדשן terumat hadeshen
*trumas hadeshen*. So,
so the כל הלילה *kol halayla* sort of, you know, is in
the middle of, is in a פסוק *pasuk* that's talking about burning
the עולה *ola* on the מזבח *mizbeach*, but it's also juxtaposed to
the תרומת הדשן terumat hadeshen *trumas hadeshen*. Alright, so, so what's,
so that's sort of saying both the burning is the whole night
and the תרומת הדשן terumat hadeshen, *trumas hadeshen* can take place the
whole night and it's considered ashes throughout the night. So the גמרא
*Gemara* says how do you deal with it? חלקייהו *chalkeyu*, you split
the night. חציו להקטרה וחציו להרמה *chetzyo l'haktara v'chetzyo l'harama*. So it
doesn't really mean the whole night is divided between והקטיר *v'hiktir* and
והרים *v'herim*. So the first half is considered, you know, still a
מצוה *mitzvah* of burning, and the second half is the taking of
the ashes. Now, again, that's not absolute. If something really isn't burnt
at all, there's still a מצוה *mitzvah* to burn it after חצות
*chatzos*. If something is already totally ashes, it's already totally ashes after,
before חצות *chatzos*. But if something's in a middle category, so the
emphasis of the first half of the night is burning, so if
it's still in the first half we'll look at it that there's
still a מצוה *mitzvah* to burn, and the emphasis of the second
half of the night is תרומת הדשן terumat hadeshen *trumas hadeshen* and
ashes, so in that case we'll look at a middle situation as
if it's already ashes. So that's what, that's why it matters and
it's clearly דאורייתא *d'oraisa* because it's about מועלין או לא מועלין בהן
*mo'elin o lo mo'elin bahen*. So מתיב רב כהנא *masiv Rav Kahana*,
so רב כהנא *Rav Kahana* does not like this, he challenged. וכל
יום תורם את המזבח מקריאת הגבר *v'chol yom torem es hamizbeach mikrias
hagever*. So this is what we teach in יומא *Yoma*. Every day,
you know, the normal כהן *kohein* would do תרומת הדשן terumat hadeshen
*trumas hadeshen* from the cock-crowing, או סמוך לו מלפניו ומאחריו *o samuch
lo milfanav u-me-acharav* or right around it a little before a little
after. ביום הכפורים בחצות *b'Yom Hakippurim b'chatzos*, on יום כיפור *Yom Kippur*
he would do it at midnight, ברגלים baregalim, באשמורת הבקר *bergalim b'ashmores
haboker*.
And on the רגלים regalim, *regalim* he would do it at the
first watch, like a third into the night, because there would be
so many sacrifices and so many ashes and you had to tend
the altar and pile up the ashes in the middle, so you
needed more time, so you do the תרומת הדשן terumat hadeshen *trumas
hadeshen* in the first third of the night. But problem is, look,
you're doing the תרומת הדשן *trumas hadeshen* in the first third of
the night, and you said based on the פסוק *pasuk* that only
from חצות *chatzos* and onward was the time of תרומת הדשן *trumas
hadeshen*. How is that going to work?
So,
אמר רבי יוחנן *amar Rabbi Yochanan*, so
says רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*,
so there's a question of רש"י *Rashi* and תוספות *Tosfos* whether רבי
יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* is saying something totally new or just slightly tweaking
what we've said before. I'm going to read it like רש"י *Rashi*
that he's just slightly tweaking what we've said before. Said רבי יוחנן
ממשמע שנאמר *Rabbi Yochanan mimashma shene'emar*, since the פסוק *pasuk* says כל
הלילה *kol halayla*, איני יודע שעד הבקר *eini yode'a she-ad haboker*? If
it says that you know you burn it the whole night, I
know it means until the morning. So why does it say מה
תלמוד לומר עד הבקר *ma talmud lomar ad haboker*? Why does it
say until the morning? תן בקר לבוקר *ten boker l'boker*. Give a
morning to the morning. של לילה. Okay, so he's first of all
going to read the בוקר boker as the בוקר boker of the
תרומת הדשן. In the morning you do the תרומת הדשן, but because
it didn't have to say עד בוקר, ad boker, that's actually saying
that there's a morning before the morning, that you do it even
before the morning. And what does that tell you? הלכך, hilkach, כל
יומא מקריאת הגבר. kol yoma mikras hagever. Normally you do it at
the cock crowing. סגי איסגי, sagi isagi, that suffices. ביומא דכיפורי משום
חולשא דכהן גדול מחצות. beyoma dekippuri mishum chulsha dekohen gadol mechatzos. On
Yom Kippur because of the weakness of the כהן גדול, kohen gadol,
you do it already, he's going to be so busy, so you
already start this as חצות. By the way, that sounds like it's
the כהן גדול kohen gadol who's doing the תרומת הדשן on Yom
Kippur, that's a debate.
ברגלים, on the רגלים, regalim דנפישי קרבנות, denefishi korbanos, there's a lot
of קרבנות, korbanos, דקדמי אתו ישראל מאשמורת הראשונה, dekadmi asu yisrael me'ashmora
harishona, and that there's so many people
gathering and there's so many קרבנות, so then you do it מאשמורת
הראשונה, me'ashmora harishona, from the first watch. כדתני kidtani like we taught,
סיפא לא הייתה קריאת הגבר מגעת עד שהייתה עזרה מלאה מישראל.
seifa lo hay'sa krias hagever magaa ad
she'hay'sa azara male'a miyisrael. Okay, so the cock didn't crow in the
רגלים until the עזרה azara was filled with ישראל. Yisrael. Now he
didn't really seem to explain anything. That whole idea of like is
it busy or not busy and do we do it early is
all very nice, but how do we still get our חצות idea
with this idea of a בוקר boker to the בוקר? boker? So
the way רש"י says it is, because remember we said that if
the stuff is already burnt before חצות, it's already ashes, then it's
already ashes and the מצווה mitzvah is done. So what רש"י is
saying is, that we learn two things from the פסוקים. pesukim. One
is, the first half of the night, the focus is הקטרה haktara.
and therefore something in a middle category will still be seen as
requiring הקטרה. haktara In the second half of the night, the focus
is תרומת הדשן and therefore something in a middle category by the
time you get to the second half of the night is considered
that the מצווה mitzvah is done and that's what that's considered. However,
just because that's the emphasis of the first half and the emphasis
of the second half, it doesn't mean they're exclusive. So for example,
if you had some meat that wasn't burned after חצות, you would
still have to burn it. It still requires being burned. It's not
exclusive, you still do הקטרה haktara the second half of the night.
Similarly, the תרומת הדשן, it's not exclusive the second half. The תן
בוקר לבוקרו של ראשון ten boker lebokro shel rishon means you can
make it earlier as situations require. So if it requires moving the
תרומת הדשן to the first half of the night, that's okay. All
right, but that's what the תן בוקר לבוקרו של ראשון ten boker
lebokro shel rishon is saying. So according to
רש"י, halachically the whole night is kosher for הקטרה haktara and if
something isn't burned and it's after חצות, you still have to put
it back up and burn it. And halachically the whole night is
kosher for תרומת הדשן and if you have to do it really
early you can do it really early. Okay, however, the first half
the emphasis is הקטרה and the second half the emphasis is תרומת
הדשן and that makes a difference for the meat that is burned
but not fully turned into ashes. Okay, that was a lot. We
will end with this here.